Guide to the John L. Margrave academic papers, 1952-1995 MS 505
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
John L. Margrave academic papers
1952-1995 [Bulk 1970-1995]
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Margrave, John L., 1924-2003
MS 505
35.25 Linear Feet (41 boxes)
The academic papers of Chemistry Professor and Dean of Advanced Studies and Research John L. Margrave reflect the daily business of his career at Rice University, and his involvement with Gulf Universities Research Consortium (GURC), Houston Area Research Center (HARC), High Temperature Science, and Marchem, Incorporated.
(41 boxes)
Biographical Note
John L. Margrave was born April 13, 1924 in Kansas City, Kansas. He served in the U.S. Army's Signal Corps from 1941 until 1968, on active duty from 1943 through 1946. Margrave earned his B.S. in Engineering Physics in 1948 and his Ph.D. in Chemistry in 1950 from the University of Kansas in Lawrence, Kansas, where he was a Summerfield Scholar and a Slosson Fellow. He spent twenty months as a Postdoctoral Fellow with the Atomic Energy Commission in the Department of Chemistry at Berkeley from 1951 to 1952. He also was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1960.
Margrave taught Chemistry from 1952 to 1963 at the University of Wisconsin. He began his career at Rice University as a professor of chemistry in 1963. From 1967 through 1972 he was professor and chair of Rice's department of chemistry, and from 1972 until 1980 as dean of Advanced Studies and Research. In 1980 he was named vice-president of Advanced Studies and Research, a position he held until 1986. That year he was named the E. D. Butcher Professor of Chemistry, a title he kept until his death on December 18, 2003 from complications following heart surgery.
Margrave's laboratory at Rice University pioneered the following processes: synthetic studies of the carbine-analog SiF2; research in liquid metals at high temperatures through the electromagnetic levitation and heating of conducting samples coupled with high pressure drop calorimetry; a technique for X-ray powder diffraction studies of samples at high pressures; the use of high temperature mass spectroscopy to study fluorides, oxyfluorides, sulfides, and other species; low temperature reactions of metal atoms, dimers, and small clusters with H2O, ROH, R2O, NH3, CO, CO2, and other Lewis bases; reactions of elemental fluorine in low-temperature matrices and with oxides and nitrides; and studies of liquid metals by levitation techniques, including microgravity. Margrave's special fields of interest included High Temperature Chemistry; Fluorine Chemistry; Optical, Infrared, ESR, Matrix-Isolation and Mass Spectrometry; High Pressure Chemistry; Thermochemistry; and Levitation Calorimetry. He was the recipient of numerous awards, including an Alfred P. Sloan Research Fellowship, an American Chemical Society Award in Fluorine Chemistry, and a Kiekhofer Memorial Teaching Award. He was included in Who's Who in America's 1976-1977 edition. Margrave belonged to numerous professional societies such as the American Chemical Society, the National Academy of Sciences, the American Institute of Chemists, and the American Society for Mass Spectrometry. He authored more than 800 publications and was editor of the journal High Temperature Science from 1968 through at least 1995 and Refractory Materials Science from 1976 to 1977. From 1970 through 1976 he also co-edited the Materials Science and Technology Series and, from 1975 to 1976, the Proceedings of the American Society for Mass Spectrometry. In addition, Margrave was a member of a number of editorial boards, including the Journal of Physical Chemistry, Annual Review of Physical Chemistry, and Advances in High Temperature Chemistry. Additionally, Margrave served on many advisory committees, including the Advisory Committee for Reactor Chemistry at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory, the Defense Advanced Research Project Agency's Materials Research Council, and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Advisory Panel for Space Processing.
During his career at Rice University Margrave served as chairman of the Committee on the Undergraduate Curriculum for 1965-1971 and the Graduate Council from 1972-1986. In addition he served on the University Council from 1972-1986, the Research Council 1971-1986, the Tenure Review Committee from 1972-1986, and the Committee on Affirmative Action from 1969-1985, which he chaired from 1969-1973. Other committees upon which Margrave served included the University Space Committee from 1980-1986 and the Graduate House Advisory Committee from 1983-1986. Margrave also became director of the Rice Design Center in 1972 and was a member of the Rice Quantum Institute beginning in 1979. He was also president and then director of Sigma Xi, the scientific research society, from 1986 until 1992.
Margrave delivered numerous international lectures and served as a consultant to many industries and government entities, including the Argonne National Laboratory, Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory, and the Solar Energy Research Institute. He established Marchem, Incorporated, a consulting firm and research lab, and was involved with the Houston Area Research Center (HARC) and the Gulf Universities Research Consortium (GURC). He married Mary Lou Davis, granddaughter of a former Kansas governor, in 1950.
The Gulf Universities Research Consortium (GURC) was formed in 1965. It was an interdisciplinary collaboration between industries and Gulf of Mexico universities designed to further research and development capabilities. Businesses such as Arco Oil and Gas Company, the Mitchell Energy and Development Corporation, and Dresser Industries often co-sponsored research projects. GURC relied on the expertise of knowledgeable professionals in economics, chemistry, anthropology, agri-economics, and ecology. The organization's founders specifically worked to develop programs and research that were in the public interest or of common concern to its members and affiliates. Affiliates included the University of Alabama, Tulane University, Southern Methodist University, and the University of Miami. The last correspondence related to GURC, dated 1983, indicates that the consortium disbanded sometime after that date.
The Houston Area Research Center (HARC) was an independent, non-profit corporation established to undertake studies associated with the development of new and emerging technologies. In addition, the corporation sought to carry out research focusing on the social, economic, and environmental consequences of alternate technologies, and to provide a setting for research and technology-related learning through workshops, seminars, and conferences. HARC was formed by a partnership of Rice University, the University of Houston, and Texas A&M University. It grew to include the University of Texas at Austin. It promoted the economic growth of east Texas and focused its attention on developing applied research centers such as the Laser Application Research Center, the Advanced Studies Institute, the National Dynamic Test Center, and the Technological Support for Health Systems center. While no definitive date for the beginning of HARC is located in the collection, it appears that it began operations in 1980. The last dated correspondence in the Margrave papers related to HARC is 1989.
High Temperature Science began publication in 1969. It was formed to foster the theoretical and practical uses of high temperature science. Margrave was one of its initial incorporators. He served as its editor from 1969 until at least 1995, the last year for which material was found in the collection. In 1975 it became known as High Temperature Science and Energy Technology and later as High Temperature and Materials Science. Academic Press originally published the journal, but lack of subscriptions caused that press to cease sponsoring publication. In 1977 Humana Press took over as publisher.
Margrave formed Marchem, Incorporated in 1969. The company started as a direct result of Margrave's and his chemistry associates' experimentation and development of CFX—a high temperature lubricant incorporating the fluorination of carbon (thus, the CF). Marchem's beginning goal was to produce and sell CFX samples. Marchem also operated as a consulting firm and research lab with expertise in high temperature chemistry. In addition, the company helped develop the LaMar process (a combination of the names of its developers—Margrave and Dr. R. J. Lagow, another Rice chemist). The process produced a product known as "FluoroKote," a fluorinated coating for plastics and rubbers. Both of these developments made possible the creation or improvement of many new products such as wax paper, surgical gloves, inner tubes, and rubber washers.
Scope and Contents
The academic papers of Chemistry Professor and Dean of Advanced Studies and Research John L. Margrave reflect the daily business of his career at Rice University, and his involvement with Gulf Universities Research Consortium (GURC), Houston Area Research Center (HARC), High Temperature Science, and Marchem, Incorporated.
See detailed descriptions at the begining of each of the 13 series.
List of abbreviations used: AAAS – American Association for the Advancement of Science; AAU – Association of American Universities; AAUP – American Association of University Professors; ACS- American Chemical Society; AEC – Atomic Energy Commission; AFOSR – Air Force Office of Scientific Research; AFWL – Air Force Weapons Laboratory; AIEC – Association of Independent Engineering Colleges; ANROTCCU – Association of NROTC Colleges and Universities; ARCS – Achievement Rewards for College Scientists; AROD – Army Research Office – Durham; ARPA – Advanced Research Projects Agency (Associated with MRC); ASLE – American Society of Lubricating Engineers; ASMS – American Society for Mass Spectrometry; AWU – Associated Western Universities; BDM – The BDM Corporation; CBTCUS – Coordinating Board, Texas College and University; System CCR – Council for Chemical Research (See also U/ITT); CDR – Critical Design Review (DARPA/AFWL); CGS – Council of Graduate Schools; CODAN – Committee on Data Needs; CRR – Chemistry Research Resource Program; CRSSR – Chemical Retaliatory Stockpile Status Review; DARPA – Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency; DOE – Department of Energy; DOT – Department of Transportation; DTST – Defense Technologies Study Team; ERDA – Energy Research and Development Administration; EREF – Energy Research and Education Foundation; ESCA – Electron Spectrometer for Chemical Analysis; GURC – Gulf Universities Research Consortium; HARC – Houston Area Research Center; HEW – Health, Education, and Welfare Department; HGAC – Houston-Galveston Area Council; HTS – High Temperature Science; ICSA – Institute for Computer Services and Applications; IIE – Institute of International Education; LCMMD – Laser Countermeasure Materials Development and Technology; NAS – National Academy of Sciences; NASA – National Aeronautic and Space Administration; NBS – National Bureau of Standards (U.S. Department of Commerce); NCURA – National Council for University Research Administrators; NIH – National Institutes of Health; NRC – National Research Council; NRL – Naval Research Lab; NSERC – National Solar Energy Research Consortium; NSF – National Science Foundation; ONR – Office of Naval Research; ORAU – Oak Ridge Associated Universities (Associated with Oak Ridge National Laboratory); ORNL – Oak Ridge National Laboratory; REDDI – Rice Engineering Design and Development Institute; SERI – Solar Energy Research Institute; SREB – Southern Regional Education Board; STAMPS – Scientific Technological Aspects of Materials Processing in Space (under the NRC); STTF – Solar Thermal Test Facilities; TAS – Texas Academy of Sciences; URA – Universities Research Association; USARO – U.S. Army Research Office; USRA – Universities Space Research Association; UTRC – United Technologies Research Center)
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred by the Rice University Chemistry Department, Feb. 2003.
Arrangement note
The academic papers of Chemistry Professor and Dean of Advanced Studies and Research John L. Margrave include 13 series:
Missing Title
Series I – Chemistry Department/Norma Komplin T.A. Papers, 1953-1979. 1 lin. ft.
Series II – Correspondence, 1970-1995 [Bulk 1970-1990]. 2 lin. ft.
Series III – Gulf Universities Research Consortium (GURC), 1965-1983. 1 lin. ft.
Series IV – Houston Area Research Center (HARC), 1980-1989. 1 lin. ft.
Series V - High Temperature Science, 1967-1995. 2.5 lin. ft.
Series VI – Marchem, Incorporated, 1972-1985. 1.5 lin. ft.
Series VII – Meetings, 1970-1988 [Bulk 1974-1985]. 14.5 lin. ft.
Series VIII – National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA), 1971-1982. 1 lin. ft.
Series IX – Research Group, 1964-1979 [Bulk 1969-1978]. 1 lin. ft.
Series X – Reviews/Proposals, 1969-1985. 2 lin. ft.
Series XI – Rice University, 1970-1989 [Bulk 1972-1986. 3.75 lin. ft.
Series XII – Subject Files, 1952-1996 [Bulk 1970-1991]. 2 lin. ft.
Series XIII – Writings, 1952-1995. 2 lin. ft.
Index Terms
Subjects
Education; Chemists; Chemistry; Universities and colleges
Document Types
notes; corrrespondence
Subjects (Persons)
Margrave, John L., 1924-2003
Subjects (Corporations)
Gulf Universities Research Consortium.; Houston Area Research Center.; Rice University. Office of Advanced Studies and Research.; William M. Rice Institute--faculty.; Marchem, Incorporated.; Rice University. Department of Chemistry.
- Series I: Chemistry Department/Norma Komplin T.A. Papers, 1953-1979, 221767
  Scope and Contents note
  The series Chemistry Department/Norma Komplin T.A. Papers contains material related to the Rice University Chemistry Department, including correspondence; postdoctoral applications; course syllabi; student papers, exams, lists, and grades. Also included are the papers of Margrave's teaching assistant, Norma Komplin. These consist of her writings, course materials, and chemical test results.
  - Subseries A: Chemistry Department, 221786
    - Chemistry 104, 221825 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 105, 221824 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 106, 221823 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 120, 221822 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 158, Spring 1953, 221821 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 265, 221820 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 460, 221819 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 610, 221818 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 611, 221817 (Box 1)
    - Chemical Education, 221816 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry Courses, 1972, 1973, 1977, 221815 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry Under Extreme Conditions Course, 221814 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1973, 221813 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1976, 221812 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1979, 221811 (Box 1)
    - Cumulative and Qualifying Exams, 221810 (Box 1)
    - Cumulative Exam Schedules, 221809 (Box 1)
    - Electron Spectroscopy Course, 221808 (Box 1)
    - Exam Correspondence, 221807 (Box 1)
    - Exam Notices, 221806 (Box 1)
    - Finances, 221805 (Box 1)
    - Innovative Teaching Conference, 221804 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 221803 (Box 1)
    - Oral Exam Committees, 221802 (Box 1)
    - Placement Exam Results, 221801 (Box 1)
    - Postdocs, Applications, 221800 (Box 1)
    - Postdocs, Bonus Correspondence, 221799 (Box 1)
    - Postdocs, Bonus Material, 221798 (Box 1)
    - Postdocs, Correspondence, 1972, 221797 (Box 1)
    - Postdocs, Correspondence, 1973, 221796 (Box 1)
    - Postdocs, Correspondence, 1974, 221795 (Box 1)
    - Postdocs, Correspondence, 1976-, 221794 (Box 1)
    - Postdocs, Correspondence, Regrets, 221793 (Box 1)
    - Postdocs, Miscellaneous, 221792 (Box 1)
    - Postdocs, Notices, 221791 (Box 1)
    - Student Grades, 221790 (Box 1)
    - Student Lists, 221789 (Box 1)
    - Student Papers, 221788 (Box 1)
    - Tentative Courses, 221787 (Box 1)
  - Subseries B: Norma Komplin T.A. Papers, 221768
    - Chemistry 101, 221785 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 103, 221784 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 104, 221783 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 495 Term Papers, 221782 (Box 1)
    - Chemistry 801, Photochemistry, 221781 (Box 1)
    - Crystal Chemistry, 221780 (Box 1)
    - Cumes (Cumulative Exams), 221779 (Box 1)
    - Diamond Morphology Photographs, 221778 (Box 1)
    - Drawings and Kestrel, 221777 (Box 1)
    - HCI Addition Studies, 221776 (Box 1)
    - Jeol SEM, 221775 (Box 1)
    - MRS001 Thickness Measurements, 221774 (Box 1)
    - Organic Reaction Sheets, 221773 (Box 1)
    - Resume, 221772 (Box 1)
    - Temperature Studies, 221771 (Box 1)
    - Writings, 221770 (Box 1)
    - Xray Diffraction, 221769 (Box 1)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1970-1995, 221680
  The Correspondence series comprises the general correspondence to and from the various organizations and associations with which Margrave was involved, as well as letters of recommendation for Margrave's former students, and letters to and from specific individuals, businesses, and organizations such as the American Chemical Society, Houston attorneys Baker & Botts, and the General Electric Corporation.
  Within the Gulf Universities and Research Consortium (GURC) series are the articles of incorporation and bylaws; board of directors and executive committee agendas, minutes, and correspondence; proposals; reports; and general correspondence.
  Researchers are also encouraged to look in Series IX: Research Group (Boxes 29 and 30) and Series XI: Rice, General Correspondence (Boxes 36 and 37) for other letters of recommendation.
  - Subseries A: Chronological, 221744
    - 1970, 221766 (Box 2)
    - 1971, 221765 (Box 2)
    - 1972, 221764 (Box 2)
    - 1973, 221763 (Box 2)
    - 1974, 221762 (Box 2)
    - 1975, 221761 (Box 2)
    - 1976, 221760 (Box 2)
    - 1977, 221759 (Box 2)
    - 1978, 221758 (Box 2)
    - 1979, 221757 (Box 2)
    - 1980, 221756 (Box 2)
    - 1981, 221755 (Box 2)
    - 1982, 221754 (Box 2)
    - 1983, 221753 (Box 2)
    - 1984, 221752 (Box 2)
    - 1985, 221751 (Box 2)
    - 1986, 221750 (Box 2)
    - 1987, 221749 (Box 2)
    - 1988, 221748 (Box 2)
    - 1989, 221747 (Box 2)
    - 1990, 221746 (Box 2)
    - 1995, 221745 (Box 2)
  - Subseries B: Alphabetical, 221681
    - ACS, 221743 (Box 2)
    - Arnold, George, 221742 (Box 2)
    - Baker & Botts, Attorneys-at-Law, 221741 (Box 2)
    - Bell Labs, 221740 (Box 2)
    - Calvo, Francisco Gnecco, 221739 (Box 2)
    - Cameron Fairchild & Associates, 221738 (Box 2)
    - Certainteed Corporation, 221737 (Box 2)
    - Chemical Technology, 221736 (Box 2)
    - Corning Glass, 221735 (Box 2)
    - Dow Chemical, 221734 (Box 2)
    - Du Pont, 221733 (Box 2)
    - Engineering Societies Library, 221732 (Box 2)
    - Exxon, 221731 (Box 2)
    - Fresenius Award, 221730 (Box 2)
    - General Electric, 221729 (Box 2)
    - International Journal of Thermophysics, 221728 (Box 2)
    - Inventor of the Year Award, 221727 (Box 2)
    - Inventor of the Year Award, 221726 (Box 2)
    - Journal of Organometallic Chemistry, 221725 (Box 2)
    - Kobayashi, Riki, 221724 (Box 2)
    - Letters of Recommendation, A-Ba, 221723 (Box 2)
    - Letters of Recommendation, Be-E, 221722 (Box 2)
    - Letters of Recommendation, F-G, 221721 (Box 2)
    - Letters of Recommendation, H, 221720 (Box 2)
    - Letters of Recommendation, I-Ka, 221719 (Box 2)
    - Letters of Recommendation, Kn-L, 221718 (Box 2)
    - Letters of Recommendation, Mahajan, 221717 (Box 2)
    - Letters of Recommendation, Me-Parks, 221716 (Box 2)
    - Letters of Recommendation, Perry, 221715 (Box 2)
    - Letters of Recommendation, Ph-S, 221714 (Box 2)
    - Letters of Recommendation, T-Wang, 221713 (Box 3)
    - Letters of Recommendation, We-Z, 221712 (Box 3)
    - Livermore Lab, 221711 (Box 3)
    - McGraw-Hill, 221710 (Box 3)
    - NAS, 221709 (Box 3)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, 221708 (Box 3)
    - NBS, 221707 (Box 3)
    - NRC, 221706 (Box 3)
    - NSF, 221705 (Box 3)
    - Pullman Kellogg, 221704 (Box 3)
    - Presidential Prizes for Innovation, 221703 (Box 3)
    - Requests for Information/Reprints, 221702 (Box 3)
    - Rossini, Frederick, 1971-1973, 221701 (Box 4)
    - Rossini, Frederick, 1974, 221700 (Box 4)
    - Rossini, Frederick, 1975, 221699 (Box 4)
    - Rossini, Frederick, 1976-1977, 221698 (Box 4)
    - Rossini, Frederick, 1978-, 221697 (Box 4)
    - Sandia Labs, 221696 (Box 4)
    - SERI, 221695 (Box 4)
    - Sloan Foundation, 221694 (Box 4)
    - Space Program, 221693 (Box 4)
    - Springer-Verlag, 221692 (Box 4)
    - Stone, Wagner & Aubel, Attorneys-at-Law, 221691 (Box 4)
    - STTF, 221690 (Box 4)
    - Texas Congressional Delegation, 221689 (Box 4)
    - Texas Southern University, 221688 (Box 4)
    - Undated, 221687 (Box 4)
    - Union Carbide, 221686 (Box 4)
    - University of Houston, 221685 (Box 4)
    - USARO, 221684 (Box 4)
    - Welch Foundation, 221683 (Box 4)
    - Williams, T. Francon, 221682 (Box 4)
- Series III: Gulf Universities Research Consortium (GURC), 1965-1983, 221651
  - Articles of Incorporation/Bylaws, 221679 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors, Agendas, 221678 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors, Correspondence, 221677 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors, Minutes, 221676 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors, Miscellaneous, 221675 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Enhanced Oil Recovery, Correspondence, 221674 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Enhanced Oil Recovery, Drafts, 221673 (Box 5, Folder 7-9)
  - Enhanced Oil Recovery, Miscellaneous, 221672 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Enhanced Oil Recovery, Reports, 221671 (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
  - Executive Committee, Agendas, 221670 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee, Correspondence, 221669 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Executive Committee, Minutes, 221668 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Financial Reports, 221667 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - General Correspondence, 1975-1976, 221666 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1977-1978, 221665 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1979, 221664 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1980, 221663 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1981-1983, 221662 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Industry/University Relations, 221661 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 221660 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 221659 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Newsclippings, 221658 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters, 221657 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Notes, 221656 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Ocean Margins Drilling, 221655 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Outer Continental Shelf Technology Program, 221654 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Proposals, 221653 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Reports, 221652 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Houston Area Research Center (HARC), 1980-1989, 221617
  The series Houston Area Research Center (HARC) contains papers related to board of directors and executive committee meetings. It also includes articles of incorporation, and bylaws, as well as meeting files, general correspondence, proposals, and reports.
  - Articles of Incorporation, 221650 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors, Agendas, 1982-1983, 221649 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors, Agendas, 1984, 221648 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors, Agendas, 1985-1986, 221647 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors, Bylaws, 221646 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors, General Correspondence, 221645 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors, Member Lists, 221644 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors, Minutes, 221643 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors, Miscellaneous, 221642 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors, Resolutions, 221641 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - HARC Corollary, 221640 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1982, 221639 (Box 7, Folder 12)